## Contact

shivam.patel1606@gmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/shivamhp (LinkedIn)

# Top Skills

Python

Java

C

## Languages

Gujarati (Native or Bilingual) English (Full Professional) French (Elementary) Hindi (Full Professional)

#### Certifications

**Data Science Ethics** 

Process Mining: Data Science in Action

Data Analysis with Python

## Honors-Awards

ACM ICPC Chennai Provincial Programming Contest NATA GUJ - ACPC, 2016 "Most Diligent Student" Award Br. Ben Judge Trophy Goyal Memorial Scholarship

#### **Publications**

Topic Modeling Based Extractive Text Summarization

Gandhipedia: A one-stop Al-enabled portal for browsing Gandhian literature, life-events and his social network

# **Shivam Patel**

MISM @ CMU | Ex- IIT Gandhinagar, IIT Bombay, NTU Singapore | Gold Medalist | SRM Alumnus | NLP | Text Mining Chennai

# Summary

Namaste!

I am Shivam Patel, a graduate student at Carnegie Mellon University pursuing the Master of Information Systems Management program.

I am an enthusiastic software developer, a curious data analyst, a programmer, an engineer and a motivated life-long student trying to make the best out of life! Being a proactive problem solver, I possess excellent interpersonal skills. I believe in the power of diversity and collaboration.

I am mainly interested in Data Science, Business Analytics, Natural Language Processing, Information Retrieval, Text Mining and everything in their orbits.

Before CMU, I worked as a Junior Research Fellow at the Indian Institute of Technology Gandhinagar. I completed my Bachelor of Technology in Computer Science and Engineering (Gold Medalist) from the SRM Institute of Science and Technology, Chennai, India. During my undergraduate studies, I have interned at NTU Singapore, IIT Bombay and IIT Gandhinagar.

And yes! My inbox is always open. Let's connect! ♂

# Experience

Microsoft Learn Student Ambassadors SRM Mentor September 2021 - September 2021 (1 month)

Mentored participants in the hackathon, 'Resonate' conducted by the Microsoft Club at SRM

GovHack
Participant
August 2021 - August 2021 (1 month)
Australia

Participated in the largest open data hackathon in the Southern Hemisphere

Indian Institute of Technology Gandhinagar 1 year 6 months

Junior Research Fellow September 2020 - July 2021 (11 months) Gandhinagar, Gujarat, India

Project: Gandhipedia

- Gandhipedia is a project of national importance which aims at building a onestop Al-enabled portal for browsing Mahatma Gandhi's literature, life events, and social networks
- This project is a joint initiative of IIT Kharagpur, IIT Gandhinagar and NCSM, Kolkata, under the aegis of The Ministry of Culture, Government of India
- As a core team member, digitized 100 volumes of The Collected Works of Mahatma Gandhi and the 7 key texts Mahatma Gandhi wrote. Implemented Elasticsearch across this extensive digitized data to build an efficient search for the user query on our portal
- Incorporated virtual tours of the core sites visited by the Mahatma
- Heavily contributed to developing the front and the back end of Gandhipedia to add numerous interactive functionalities on the web portal
- Single-handedly built a robust Twitter Bot (@Gandhipedia150) for Gandhipedia that is constantly posting the essential excerpts of Mahatma Gandhi's writings and the rare images of Gandhiji to influence the people to follow his vision and thoughts in day to day life

# **Teaching Assistant**

January 2021 - January 2021 (1 month)

Gandhinagar, Gujarat, India

- Teaching Assistant for the faculty development program under the 'Third Phase of Technical Education Quality Improvement Programme (TEQIP-III)' initiative of the Ministry of Education, Government of India
- Course Title: Online Short Course on Data Science & Analytics
- Around 45 faculties from various institutions across India participated to learn from the course

Research Intern (Full-Time)

## February 2020 - August 2020 (7 months)

Gandhinagar, Gujarat, India

#### **IEEE**

Web and Publicity Chair October 2020 - December 2020 (3 months)

International Workshop on Fair and Interpretable Learning Algorithms (FILA 2020) in conjunction with IEEE International Conference on Big Data (IEEE BigData 2020), Atlanta Marriott Marquis, Atlanta, GA, USA.

Date of Conference: December 10 - 13, 2020

## MIT COVID-19 Challenge

Invited Participant August 2020 - August 2020 (1 month)

- Was 1 among 3725+ applicants invited to participate in the "MIT COVID19
  Challenge India Turing The Tide", a 48-hour virtual event aimed at
  addressing the most pressing issues arising from the ongoing COVID-19 crisis.
- Build an innovative solution to combat poor quality control and fraud during the pandemic.

Indian Institute of Technology Gandhinagar 6 months

Research Intern (Part-Time) August 2019 - November 2019 (4 months) Gandhinagar, Gujarat, India

Project: Tabular Information Extraction from Scientific Articles

- In the next phase of the project, performed a grid search on the attributes created for the developed CRF++ model to discover the best possible set of attributes
- Post-processed the output of our CRF++ model to achieve a better performance score on classification output
- Worked on building a statistical model to process the output generated by the CRF++ model to achieve stronger tabular information extraction results

Research Intern (SRIP)
June 2019 - July 2019 (2 months)
Gandhinagar, Gujarat, India

Garidilliagar, Gujarat, Ilidia

Project: Tabular Information Extraction from Scientific Articles

- 1 among 144 students selected (19,000+ applicants) for SRIP 2019
- As a part of the project, bench-marked the Cornell University arXiv Dataset (102 GB) to develop machine learning/deep learning models for automatic detection and extraction of tabular data present within scientific articles in PDF format with high accuracy, efficiency, and in a scalable fashion.
- Developed a CRF++ (Conditional Random Fields ++) model to automate the tabular information extraction on the generated dataset

Indian Institute of Technology, Bombay Software Development Intern May 2018 - July 2018 (3 months)

Mumbai, Maharashtra, India

Project: Development of Sunbird Analytics

- 1 among 73 students selected (3300+ applicants) for the Eklavya Summer Internship
- Added an 'Analytics' tab on Sunbird portal that was programmed to display the visual analysis of any course on Sunbird

Corporate Gurukul
Trainer and Counsellor
February 2018 - May 2018 (4 months)
SRM Institute of Science and Technology, Chennai, India

GAIP (Global Academic Internship Programme) Champion | Winter Batch 2017

- One among the few selected from the GAIP Winter Batch 2017, to train and counsel the participants of GAIP Summer Batch 2018, to help them gain the prerequisite knowledge required for their GAIP
- Delivered lectures on Hadoop set-up, Linux, Java and Python

Nanyang Technological University Academic Intern December 2017 - January 2018 (2 months) Singapore

 Attended the Global Academic Internship Programme on 'Big Data Analytics using Artificial Neural Networks' in association with Hewlett-Packard Enterprise Education Services and Strategic Technology Management Institute @ National University of Singapore (STMI@NUS) at Nanyang Technological University

- Learnt with hands-on and a project (Employee Attrition Analysis), about Hadoop and Big Data Analytics
- Tech Involved: R, Python, Java, Weka, Linux, Hadoop, MS-Excel, Analytics

Intellect Design Arena Ltd Student

August 2017 - November 2017 (4 months)

School of Design Thinking, Chennai, Tamil Nadu, India

- Studied the course, 'Design The Thinking' taught by industry professionals at 8012 FinTech Design Centre, a refreshingly unique design centre for financial institutions
- I was 1 among the 30 from SRMIST selected to attend the course

SkyLim Infotech Pvt. Ltd.
Part-Time Intern

August 2017 - October 2017 (3 months)

Chennai, Tamil Nadu, India

- Joined the team to work on a budding startup idea: "SkyLim Project & Incubation Hub", a platform to conceive an online local market platform
- Underwent training on Erlang, HTTP, XMPP, SQL (MySQL), NoSQL (MongoDB and CouchDB), Poolboy, Kafka, architectures (microservices and monolithic) and clustering, partitioning and parallelism in DB; also thoroughly looked into the DB Schema of Amazon
- Also learnt about Elixir and Phoenix

# Education

Carnegie Mellon University

Master of Information Systems Management · (August 2021 - May 2023)

SRM University

Bachelor of Technology, Computer Science and Engineering · (2016 - 2020)

Atmiya Vidya Mandir - International Residential School for Boys Higher Secondary Education, AISSCE (All India Senior School Certificate Examination) · (2014 - 2016)

St. Mary's High School, Mt. Abu, Rajasthan, India Secondary Education, ICSE (Indian Certificate of Secondary Education Examination) · (2009 - 2014)